Hi there.
Welcome to this video
where we are going to learn
about digital systems
and the digital environment.
The goal of the video is to help
you understand what a digital environment is,
and what the building blocks
of digital systems are.
In the video, firstly, we will
look at what we mean by digital devices.
Following this, we will explore
what we mean by a digital environment.
Finally, we will take a look
at what the building blocks
of digital systems are.
People in today's world
spend a lot of time using digital devices.
Computers, smartphones
and tablets are examples
of digital devices that make up
the digital environment around us.
Digital devices
help us with work and school
as well as with family
and leisure activities.
People work online with their
peers on the same project.
We can go online to pay bills
or apartment rent, and we can watch TV
shows and buy tickets
to a sports event on our digital devices.
People also use
various application programs,
commonly called apps,
to study and communicate.
We send messages and photos
using messaging apps.
People can play games on their devices
alone or with friends who are far away.
In short, most of us cannot
imagine our lives without digital devices.
Not all of the digital devices
we use are a part
of the digital environment.
A digital environment is any environment
where your digital device
is connected to the internet.
Typically, a food mixer
and a vacuum cleaner
are non-digital electric home appliances.
Some digital home appliances
have mini computers inside them.
For example, a washing machine has a mini
computer to manage washing programs.
Such devices can sometimes be updated
using special tools that connect
to the appliance using another connection
type, for example Bluetooth.
Not all of these appliances
are connected to the internet.
However, a refrigerator
with a wireless internet connection
is part of the digital environment.
Owners could use mobile
or web applications to check humidity,
temperature, or appliance status data.
Digital devices also include
computers and smartphones.
All digital devices and internet connected
appliances make up
what we call a personal network.
What devices are part
of your personal network?
How do these digital devices work?
Digital systems
help our digital devices to work,
and these systems are built with computer
programs and applications
that are called software.
Software is a broad term that includes
games, online educational systems,
text editing tools, and booking systems
to buy tickets or rent apartments.
Software can be standalone or remote.
Standalone software is installed
on the user's personal device.
For example, personal digital devices
have operating system software
which enables all of the devices,
functions, and controls
the installation of applications
such as games or a work related program.
The installed applications
use the computing resources
and settings of the personal device.
You may have noticed that older devices
have fewer computing resources.
For example,
maybe you have an old computer, phone,
or gaming system that cannot run new games
that require more computing resources.
In comparison,
other computer programs and applications
are connected to the internet,
and these online systems
run on remote computers.
These remote computers
are located somewhere else,
often far away from the user.
Access to online systems
happens thanks to software
installed locally on the personal device.
In most cases, people need browsers
to access online systems.
We can think of local
software programs as opening
a portal to powerful online resources.
Standalone applications can work offline.
For example, some games
allow users to play without the internet.
However, they can be connected
to the internet to send data
or retrieve data
from to remote computers upon request.
For example,
the results are sent to a remote computer
when the internet is available.
That way, the remote computer
can make a game leaderboard
after getting the results.
However, many games are only functional
with the internet, such as multiplayer
games that allow several users
to play together in real time.
Thus, a locally installed game
application sends data
about the user's actions
to a remote computer without any delay.
Which of your digital
devices connect to the internet?
What applications on these devices
can be used without the internet?
So in this short video,
we learned that we are
part of the digital environment
when we are using devices
that are connected to the internet.
We have also learned
That the digital systems such as
smartphones, gaming consoles and computers
work because of software
that is either standalone or remote.
Thank you for watching.
Do not forget to watch
other videos in our series.